is that it slaps you awake. You can't take anything for granted. Travel, for me, is a little bit like being in love, because suddenly all your senses are at the setting marked "on." Suddenly you're alert to the secret patterns of the world. The real voyage of discovery, as Marcel Proust famously said, consists not in seeing new sights, but in looking with new eyes. And of course, once you have new eyes, even the old sights, even your home become something different. Many of the people living in countries not their own are refugees who never wanted to leave home and ache to go back home. But for the fortunate among us, I think the age of movement brings exhilarating new possibilities. Certainly when I'm traveling, especially to the major cities of the world, the typical person I meet today will be, let's say, a half-Korean, half-German young woman living in Paris. And as soon as she meets a half-Thai, half-Canadian young guy from Edinburgh, she recognizes him as kin. She realizes that she probably has much more in common with him than with anybody entirely of Korea or entirely of Germany. So they become friends. They fall in love. They move to New York City. (Laughter) Or Edinburgh. And the little girl who arises out of their union will of course be not Korean or German or French or Thai or Scotch or Canadian or even American, but a wonderful and constantly evolving mix of all those places. And potentially, everything about the way that young woman dreams about the world, writes about the world, thinks about the world, could be something different, because it comes out of this almost unprecedented blend of cultures. Where you come from now is much less important than where you're going. More and more of us are rooted in the future or the present tense as much as in the past. And home, we know, is not just the place where you happen to be born. It's the place where you become yourself. And yet, there is one great problem with movement, and that is that it's really hard to get your bearings when you're in midair. Some years ago, I noticed that I had accumulated one million miles on United Airlines alone. You all know that crazy system, six days in hell, you get the seventh day free. (Laughter) And I began to think that really, movement was only as good as the sense of stillness that you could bring to it to put it into perspective. And eight months after my house burned down, I ran into a friend who taught at a local high school, and he said, "I've got the perfect place for you." "Really?" I said. I'm always a bit skeptical when people say things like that. "No, honestly," he went on, "it's only three hours away by car, and it's not very expensive, and it's probably not like anywhere you've stayed before." "Hmm." I was beginning to get slightly intrigued. "What is it?" "Well —" Here my friend hemmed and hawed — "Well, actually it's a Catholic hermitage." This was the wrong answer. I had spent 15 years in Anglican schools, so I had had enough hymnals and crosses to last me a lifetime. Several lifetimes, actually. But my friend assured me that he wasn't Catholic, nor were most of his students, but he took his classes there every spring. And as he had it, even the most restless, distractible, testosterone-addled 15-year-old Californian boy only had to spend three days in silence and something in him cooled down and cleared out. He found himself. And I thought, "Anything that works for a 15-year-old boy ought to work for me." So I got in my car, and I drove three hours north along the coast, and the roads grew emptier and narrower, and then I turned onto an even narrower path, barely paved, that snaked for two miles up to the top of a mountain. And when I got out of my car, the air was pulsing. The whole place was absolutely silent, but the silence wasn't an absence of noise. It was really a presence of a kind of energy or quickening. And at my feet was the great, still blue plate of the Pacific Ocean. All around me were 800 acres of wild dry brush. And I went down to the room in which I was to be sleeping. Small but eminently comfortable, it had a bed and a rocking chair and a long desk and even longer picture windows looking out on a small, private, walled garden, and then 1,200 feet of golden pampas grass running down to the sea. And I sat down, and I began to write, and write, and write, even though I'd gone there really to get away from my desk. And by the time I got up, four hours had passed. Night had fallen, and I went out under this great overturned saltshaker of stars, and I could see the tail lights of cars disappearing around the headlands 12 miles to the south. And it really seemed like my concerns of the previous day vanishing. And the next day, when I woke up in the absence of telephones and TVs and laptops, the days seemed to stretch for a thousand hours. It was really all the freedom I know when I'm traveling, but it also profoundly felt like coming home. And I'm not a religious person, so I didn't go to the services. I didn't consult the monks for guidance. I just took walks along the monastery road and sent postcards to loved ones. I looked at the clouds, and I did what is hardest of all for me to do usually, which is nothing at all. And I started to go back to this place, and I noticed that I was doing my most important work there invisibly just by sitting still, and certainly coming to my most critical decisions the way I never could when I was racing from the last email to the next appointment. And I began to think that something in me had really been crying out for stillness, but of course I couldn't hear it because I was running around so much. I was like some crazy guy who puts on a blindfold and then complains that he can't see a thing. And I thought back to that wonderful phrase I had learned as a boy from Seneca, in which he says, "That man is poor not who has little but who hankers after more." And, of course, I'm not suggesting that anybody here go into a monastery. That's not the point. But I do think it's only by stopping movement that you can see where to go. And it's only by stepping out of your life and the world that you can see what you most deeply care about and find a home. And I've noticed so many people now take conscious measures to sit quietly for 30 minutes every morning just collecting themselves in one corner of the room without their devices, or go running every evening, or leave their cell phones behind when they go to have a long conversation with a friend. Movement is a fantastic privilege, and it allows us to do so much that our grandparents could never have dreamed of doing. But movement, ultimately, only has a meaning if you have a home to go back to. And home, in the end, is of course not just the place where you sleep. It's the place where you stand. Thank you. (Applause)
es que siempre te mantienes alerta. Nada se da por sentado. Viajar para mí es un poco como estar enamorado, porque de repente todos tus sentidos se "encienden". De repente estás alerta a los patrones secretos del mundo. El verdadero viaje de descubrimiento, como famosamente dijo Marcel Proust, no consiste en ver paisajes nuevos, sino en ver con ojos nuevos. Y, por supuesto, una vez que ves con ojos nuevos hasta los viejos paisajes y tu hogar se vuelven algo diferente. Muchas de las personas que no viven en sus propios países son refugiados que nunca quisieron dejar sus hogares y anhelan volver a su hogar. Pero para los afortunados entre nosotros, creo que la era de la movilidad nos trae emocionantes posibilidades nuevas. Es cierto que cuando viajo, especialmente a las principales ciudades del mundo, el personaje típico que llego a conocer hoy día es, por ejemplo, una mujer mitad coreana y mitad alemana que vive en París. Tan pronto la joven conoce a ese chico mitad tailandés y mitad canadiense de Edimburgo, reconoce sus semejanzas. Se da cuenta de que probablemente tiene mucho más en común con él que con alguien totalmente coreano o alemán. Así que se hacen amigos; se enamoran. Se mudan a la ciudad de Nueva York. (Risas) O Edimburgo. Y la niña que nace de esa unión no será, por supuesto, ni coreana ni alemana, ni francesa ni tailandesa, ni escocesa ni canadiense, ni incluso estadounidense, sino una mezcla maravillosa y constante de todos esos sitios. Y posiblemente, la manera en que esta joven mujer sueñe, escriba, y piense acerca del mundo pueda ser algo diferente, porque surge a partir de una mezcla de culturas sin precedentes. De dónde eres es mucho menos importante que hacia dónde vas. Más y más de nosotros estamos tan enraizados al futuro o al presente, como al pasado. Y sabemos que el hogar no es el sitio donde nos tocó nacer. Es el sitio donde nos convertimos en lo que somos. Mas aún, hay un gran problema con la movilidad y es que es difícil saber cómo comportarse cuando estás en el aire. Hace unos años atrás me di cuenta de que había acumulado un millón de millas solamente con United Airlines. Todos Uds. conocen ese descabellado sistema de pasar seis días en el infierno y el séptimo te sale gratis. (Risas) Comencé a pensar que realmente la movilidad es tan buena como el sentido de quietud que eres capaz de darle para ponerla en perspectiva. Ocho meses después de la destrucción de mi casa me encontré con un amigo que enseñaba en una escuela secundaria cercana que me dijo: "Conozco el sitio perfecto para tí". "¿De veras?" le dije. Siempre soy un poco escéptico cuando la gente me dice cosas así. "No, en serio", continuó, "queda a solo tres horas en auto, no es muy caro y, posiblemente, no se parezca a ninguno de los sitios en los que has estado". "Mmm". Comenzaba a intrigarme un poco. "¿Qué es?" "Bueno..." --aquí mi amigo comenzó a vacilar--. "Bueno, es una ermita católica". No fue una buena respuesta. Con haber pasado 15 años en escuelas anglicanas, ya tenía himnos y cruces suficientes para toda una vida. De hecho, varias vidas. Pero mi amigo me aseguró que no era católico, así como tampoco la mayoría de sus estudiantes, pero todas las primaveras llevaba allí a sus alumnos. Y allí, hasta el más inquieto y distraído chico californiano de 15 años lleno de testosterona, solo tenía que pasar tres días en silencio y algo en él se tranquilizaba y se purificaba. Se encontraba a sí mismo. Así que pensé: "Todo lo que funciona con un chico de 15 años debe funcionar conmigo". Así que me subí al auto y manejé tres horas hacia el norte junto a la costa, y las vías se iban vaciando y estrechándose hasta convertirse en un camino aún más estrecho, apenas pavimentado y lleno de curvas por más de 3 km hasta la cima de la montaña. Y cuando salí del auto el aire vibraba. Todo el sitio estaba en silencio absoluto, pero el silencio no implicaba la ausencia de ruido. Era la presencia de un tipo de energía o vibración. Y a mis pies se encontraba el grandioso y tranquilo paisaje azul del océano Pacífico. A mi alrededor había más de 300 Ha de arbustos silvestres secos. Así que bajé al cuarto en el que dormiría. Pequeño, pero maravillosamente cómodo, con una cama, una mecedora, un largo escritorio, y unas ventanas aún más largas apuntando a un jardín pequeño y privado rodeado de paredes, y unos 365 metros de grama de pradera dorada extendiéndose hacia el mar. Y me senté y comencé a escribir. Y escribí y escribí, aún cuando realmente había ido para alejarme de la escritura. Cuando me levanté ya habían pasado cuatro horas. Había caído la noche, salí y me arropó un gran manto de estrellas, y podía ver las luces de los autos desaparecer alrededor del promontorio, casi 20 Km al sur. Y realmente parecía que todas mis preocupaciones del día anterior se desvanecían. El próximo día cuando desperté, ante la ausencia de teléfonos, televisiones y portátiles, el día parecía extenderse por miles de horas. Era realmente la libertad que experimentaba cuando viajaba, aunque también lo sentía profundamente como una vuelta al hogar. Y como no soy religioso no asistí a los servicios. No fui con los monjes para que me guiaran. Solo daba largos paseos por el camino del monasterio y enviaba postales a mis seres queridos. Observaba las nubes, e hice realmente lo que usualmente para mi es lo más difícil de hacer, que es hacer nada. Y comencé a regresar a este sitio, y me di cuenta que era donde hacía mi trabajo más importante, sin notarlo, y solo con quedarme quieto. Y ciertamente tomar las decisiones más importantes de la forma que nunca hubiese podido cuando estoy corriendo del último correo electrónico a la próxima diligencia. Y comencé a pensar que algo en mí realmente había comenzado a gritar pidiendo quietud, pero claro que no podía oírlo porque estaba corriendo demasiado. Era como un loco a quien le ponen una venda y luego se queja de que no puede ver. Y recordé esa frase maravillosa de Séneca que había aprendido de niño que dice: "El hombre es pobre no porque tiene poco, sino porque anhela tener más". Claro que no estoy sugiriendo que todos aquí vayan a un monasterio. Ese no es la cuestión. Pero pienso que cuando dejas de moverte es cuando puedes ver hacia dónde vas. Y solo cuando te apartas de tu vida y del mundo, puedes ver lo que realmente es importante y conseguir un hogar. He notado que muchos ahora toman la decisión consciente de sentarse en silencio por 30 minutos cada mañana para ordenar sus pensamientos en un rincón del cuarto sin sus aparatos, o se van a correr todas las tardes, o dejan sus teléfones móviles cuando van a pasar un buen rato conversando con un amigo. La movilidad es un privilegio fantástico y nos permite hacer muchas de las cosas que nuestros abuelos nunca hubiesen soñado hacer. Pero básicamente, la movilidad, solo tiene sentido si tienes un hogar al cual regresar. Y el hogar, al fin y al cabo, está no solo en el sitio en donde duermes. Es el sitio en donde estás. Gracias. (Aplausos)